When it comes to something
as life-and-death important
as what to feed ourselves
and our families,
we should rely not on
anecdotes, but on facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we continue with our
series on exercise as medicine.
And I have to say,
I was surprised by how much controversy
there is in the medical literature
over whether the apparent longevity
benefits of exercise are even real.
Whether six percent
of premature mortality
is related to physical
inactivity, nine percent,
or even 15 percent,
these estimates
are all predicated
on the presumption that
the associations found linking
inactivity to death rates
in observational studies
constitute cause-and-effect.
A classic study from the 1950's
entitled "Coronary Heart-Disease
and Physical Activity of Work"
illustrates how difficult
it can be to tease out causality
between physical activity
and longevity.
London bus drivers appeared
to have twice the risk of dying
from heart disease
compared to bus conductors
who were presumed
to be protected
by their climbing up
and down 500 to 700
steps a day
in the famous double deckers.
However, it was later revealed
in a follow up paper
"Physique of London Busmen,"
that based on the measurements
of their starting uniforms,
the bus drivers started out
significantly heavier.
Similar issues surrounding
reverse causality continue
to haunt observational exercise
studies to this day.
Is exercising enabling
good health in seniors,
or is good health
enabling exercise
in the first place?
Is inactivity leading
to chronic disease,
or is chronic disease
leading to inactivity?
Then there are
the confounding factors.
The archetypical one
being less smoking
among active individuals.
With the exception
of elite male power athletes
who may die up to nearly
five times the normal rate
(perhaps due to use
of anabolic steroids),
athletes tend to live longer
than their
sedentary counterparts,
as much as four
to eight years longer.
But think of all
the complicating elements,
especially among professionals.
Major league baseball players,
Tour de France cyclists,
and champion skiers
all live longer
than the general population.
But that doesn't mean
that necessarily has anything
to do with home runs,
bicyclettes, or the slopes.
Maybe it's partly the superior
genetic constitution
that allow
for such physical feats
in the first place
or the socioeconomic status
bestowed upon the winner.
Yes, Olympic medalists
live longer
than the general population,
but so do grandmasters of chess,
as revealed by a study subtitled
"Mind versus muscle," suggesting
it's the afforded status
rather than muscular exertion.
Winners of a Nobel Prize
or an Oscar award
similarly have
superior life expectancy.
To try to tease out
these factors,
researchers have compared
the effects
of leisure-time
physical activity
to occupational
physical activity.
If the link between exercise
and longevity were truly causal,
then the context within which
you get the same exertion
shouldn't matter.
As you can probably guess,
though, manual labor
can sometimes be associated
with a shorter,
not longer, life,
again suggesting the primacy
of confounders
like socioeconomic factors.
Is it possible
that a genetic predisposition
to physical fitness
is what accounts
for the exercise-longevity link
rather than
the physical activity itself?
In other words, is it
just genetic selection bias?
We know exercise and longevity
are associated with one another,
but instead of exercise causing
the longevity,
maybe the same
genetic predisposition
to exercise also leads
to longevity,
whether or not
you actually exercise at all.
This question was raised by
a pair of mind-blowing studies.
The first involved a comparison
of two strains of rats,
one bred to have a high
intrinsic running capacity
and the other bred to have
a low running capacity.
Then they were randomized
to either get a running wheel
or not.
Even without exercising,
the high-fitness ability rats
lived longer than those
with the low fitness ability,
but unexpectedly the provision
of running wheels
so they could all exercise
voluntarily
cut the lives
of both strains short.
Running reduced
their life expectancy.
Using twin studies,
we can show that there are also
genetic predispositions
to exercise in humans too.
When identical twins leave home
to start their separate lives,
their exercise habits are much
more likely to be "concordant"
than fraternal twins.
This means if one twin
vigorously exercises,
then the other twin
is more likely
to do the same
if they share 100 percent
of their DNA instead
of just 50 percent
like regular brothers
and sisters.
How could we tell if it's
this genetic predisposition
to exercise rather than
the actual exercise
that accounts
for athletic longevity?
Well, what about the rare cases
of identical twins
whose exercise habits diverge?
With the same DNA,
would intense physical activity
make a difference?
Apparently not.
The same mortality rates
were found in identical twins
whether they
exercised vigorously or not.
A critical analysis on whether
physical activity is a cause
of longevity concluded
"the undisputed health-related
benefits of exercise have yet
to translate into
any proven causal relationship
with longevity."
This was based on the fact
that the randomized controlled
trials in clinical populations,
suffering mostly
from neurological conditions,
have shown a drop
in premature death rates.
Exercise interventions
have failed
to show exercise extends life
among apparently healthy
individuals.
However, these
are difficult studies to run.
Take the largest such study,
where more than 1,500 older men
and women (average age 73)
were randomized to one
of three groups for five years.
A recommendation to just follow
the national guidelines
of 30 minutes a day
five days a week,
or to replace two of those
weekly sessions
with 50-minute sessions,
or to replace two
of those weekly sessions
with four four-minute bursts
of high intensity
interval training
at 90 percent
of peak heart rate.
And there ended up being
no difference in mortality rates
between the two extra exercise
groups and the control group.
This may be because
the control group
ended up exercising so much.
The control group advised
to exercise for just 30 minutes
ended up exercising
more than the group told
to boost weekly sessions
up to 50 minutes.
All participants had
the potential to be randomized
to the high-intensity group,
so the enrollees
had to be pretty fit
at baseline.
And with expectations
of health checks at years one,
three, and five,
the control group
stepped it up so much
it blurred the distinctions
between the three groups.
In our final story,
we look at the data that shows it may be
prudent to limit chronic, vigorous exercise
to no more than an hour a day
and no more than five hours a week.
How much exercise is too much?
There don't appear
to be any studies
on the longevity of marathon
or triathlon runners,
but this study in which more
than a thousand joggers
were followed
for up to a dozen years
is able to offer some insight.
Surprisingly,
the "light" joggers appeared
to have the lowest
mortality rates.
Moderate joggers
had a worse mortality rate
than light joggers.
They still did better than
that of sedentary nonjoggers,
but strenuous joggers did not.
There wasn't
a significant difference
in death rates between those
jogging more than four hours
a week and those
not jogging at all.
So, the death versus jogging
intensity graph
was a U-shaped curve,
with the lowest mortality
bottoming out among those
taking it relatively easy,
clocking one to 2.4 hours a week
over no more than three days
at a slow or average pace.
So more may not necessarily
be better.
The jogging study spurred
sensationalist headlines
like "Fast Running Can Kill,"
but the strenuous joggers
were just dying at a higher rate
compared to light joggers,
not compared to
the general population
of nonjoggers.
Here's what
a meta-analysis found
of all such similar studies:
Yes, diminishing returns,
but the only clear
mortality bump
was associated with inactivity.
However, there was
a retrospective analysis
of more than a thousand male
Olympic track and field athletes
that suggested that those
who had extraordinary
early peak performance
had lifespans shortened
by almost five years.
The regimen for peak performance
may not be the same as that
for optimum health
and longevity.
Perhaps the mantra
"exercise is medicine" metaphor
should be taken a step further,
recognizing that like any
powerful medicine there
may be a safe range of dosing.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest major book,
“How Not to Age” is out.
Check it out from your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
I actually just came out
with another small book:
an easy 100-page read on
Ozempic and other GLP-1 drugs.
Go to NutritionFacts.org
and click on “Books”
to see where you can get an e-book,
audiobook, or paperback of it.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There are no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.